[SPEAKER_00]: So, the pressure of restraint can sometimes make the mind irrational.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, do you have any advice for how to maintain perspective in the face of the irrational mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, maintaining perspective, it's gonna require you losing perspective, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maintaining perspective means developing perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can... you can know what the perspective is, but when the irrational mind is pressuring you, you're going to lose it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because otherwise, you wouldn't be pressured, or not as pressured.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it does boil down to then not acting out of the irrational mind, and feeling that grain that's trying to pull you with... to go with it, and trying to then
[SPEAKER_01]: Exert the right perspective within it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like, oh, I need to get the right perspective for this to go away.
[SPEAKER_01]: More like, no, no, no, this won't be going away.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only thing I can and should be doing is have the perspective present with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how it eventually goes away.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, really... and that's not terribly hard to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's kind of hard to not forget is to
[SPEAKER_01]: You fall back into the expectation for this pain to go away.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, whether you're doing a perspective or this, or not acting out as well, you're doing it all under this intention of... so that it goes away.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it's not going away.
[SPEAKER_01]: It won't go away because of that very reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's then more practically...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's better, from a practical point of view,
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not about it going away.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want it to go away.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want it to stay here, so that I can present it with a perspective, and then keep it there for as long as it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like as we said before, like a screaming child.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can do this or that to appease it, so it stops screaming, or you could just
[SPEAKER_01]: Repeat how things are.
[SPEAKER_01]: The actual tell it that, no, this is how it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it refuses to hear that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It continues to scream.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you just hold the picture in front of it until it calms down and accepts it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or the knocking at the door.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, but hold on, why am I bothered?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I'm bothered because I do still
[SPEAKER_01]: I carry an assumption that it shouldn't be happening and it shouldn't be anybody in front of my door because it would be better if it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I want it to not be in front of my door.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, yeah, but that's not up to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only reason you're resisting or you're still pressured by somebody in front of your door is because you still carry expectation that I want to go away from in front of my door.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want front of my door to be free and open.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, but that's not your domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: What if... so... because you start from this position of ignorance and you're just like... sometimes you're even like not aware maybe that you are like subtly, I don't know, opening the door somehow without... Well...
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no reason to mystify it like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's always.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it's true to some extent, it's irrelevant, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's relevant is the stuff that you are aware of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, then later on you might find, oh, there are those other subtle ways, but to assume the subtle ways now are responsible for this, they're not.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's what you're doing now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you now still carrying
[SPEAKER_01]: The heavy assembly.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I refuse to live under this.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want it to go away from the front of my door.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want it to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's really the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the whole training that boils down to maintaining the perspective, or presenting the perspective, or reminding yourself of the right perspective, in face of that pain that has arisen on account of that irrational pressure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Could you say that you'd be holding up that picture to the child?
[SPEAKER_03]: But, you know, it's not for the child.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, the child could scream forever, but it's for you to remember as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's for you to remember for sure, but fundamentally it's so that the child eventually learns.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can't help but want pain to go away.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can certainly make sure that it's not
[SPEAKER_01]: the root of your immediate intention, like, but I want it now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever I do, I want.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, yeah, you practice because you want to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not in that sense of through that denial, but through the sense of, no, no, I will be free from suffering when the mind stops or loses the ability to become irrational and turn against me and itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you could say... you could, like... if you practice this for a while, so you're not acting out, and then pressure comes and goes, sometimes more, sometimes less, sometimes better, sometimes worse, but overall, you're not sliding back in terms of your unwholesome actions, you're not going against the precepts, you're not losing sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, sometimes you more accurately re-establish perspective, sometimes that's just feel like too much work and you're just weathering it until it stops.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to go through some extent of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's inevitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as you're doing it, as I said, even if you're just not acting out, but even if you don't have any perspective at the time, it's still obviously a form of staying with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like, oh, this is wrong now.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no wrong for as long as you don't act out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As long as the door is not open, there is nothing wrong what you do inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, it's not the best thing you should do, but it's nowhere near the threshold of it's wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's another trick to get you to open the door.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: I might as well open the door now.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for as long as the door is not open, it's not wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: It simply isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot be.
[SPEAKER_00]: No matter how much...
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter how confused, how doubtful, how everything else you might be feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, yeah, but the door's not open.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still better than being open.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's still more right than it would have been otherwise.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is... is that the clarity about what that doorway is always available?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, whenever there is a pressure, there's a doorway.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like the... the line of... because you can...
[SPEAKER_03]: You lose sight of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, right, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But... Yeah, so...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the recollection of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think, let's say, the doorway is basically if you... if you, like, really act out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could be walking towards the door, be on the other side of the door, but not open it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, if you are constantly just sitting on the other side of the door next to the door handle, well, the pressure to open it will increase.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to recognize that as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, fundamentally, as long as you don't open it, you are safe, even if it doesn't feel like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it won't feel like that, because that's the only true safety.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the Mahārāja presented as.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the worst thing you can do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you could.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... and that's on that part.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you're on the inside,
[SPEAKER_01]: Of the house, when you're not opening the door, but you are kind of getting, like, walking past the door, examining the door, thinking about opening the door, trying to all this.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize, okay, I could stop that now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's that part we talked about before, of, like, not allowing images to take the center stage.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as we said also, I think, in one of the talks, it's like, even without them being the center stage, you already know what they are.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if I don't explicitly start thinking about things I'm being pressured and all this and that, if I were to allow it, I know exactly what I will think.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I won't.
[SPEAKER_01]: I won't allow it in the center stage.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, I'm not trying to get rid of who is in front of the door.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not trying to get rid of all these thoughts that are... that would be associated with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just keeping them into that blur.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not allowing them to crystallize through my own efforts.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they pop up on their own, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a completely different thing than if they pop up because I intended them to do so.
[SPEAKER_01]: Although it feels the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: The end result feels the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same image that popped up.
[SPEAKER_01]: But one came through your own intention, one didn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's through your own intention, that's the center stage I talk about.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's actually... there's a whole universe of difference between the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you need to arrive at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The difference is internal.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not in the content.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know if I said it in some talk or just when we were speaking without recording.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like
[SPEAKER_01]: You imagine you have like a, like a, like a, I don't know, a place with a glass in between, that is just like a, I don't know, a square meter of foot space, and there is like a transparent glass in between.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's like this on the same spot.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the only way to get from one side of that glass, like 10 centimeters, well, not even 10, like one centimeter on the other side of the glass,
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to go all the way around, completely, all the way around, to a different world, to arrive at the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You still look at the same thing that's there, on that floor.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you have the images and stuff that present themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: Untrained mind wouldn't see a difference between picking them up with your intention, and them coming up on their own.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then it would think, I need to deal with the content, I need to deal with the thoughts themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, no, you need to deal with your intention in thinking them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's that practice of not allowing them the center stage while the blurry cloud is there waiting to crystallize.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if it crystallizes on its own, you're free.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're still free.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're untouched by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it crystallizes through your own intention of picking it up, that's what touches you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the practice that can only be done indoors.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only do this practice and eventually discern this difference if the door remains closed.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you go out to deal with stuff that's in front of your door, through your techniques and managements and stuff, none of this will be applicable.
[SPEAKER_01]: This domain ceases to exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: The distinction between those two?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the distinction theoretically remains, but practical possibility of seeing it is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you need to close the door for those distinctions to start to appear.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, imagine now... Say you're not... You're... You're...
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a hindrance pressuring you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether it's the doubt, ill-will, sensuality... You know the state of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know the general cloud that's waiting there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pressuring it to start intentionally crystallizing the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you refrain... Again, I don't need to be cancelling the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the painful part, when you think you need to be changing this weight and the direction of this weather.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't actually...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't have to do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: The sole reason that any of that would be a problem is if I'm making a connection, creating a connection,
[SPEAKER_01]: Activation through intentionally crystallizing thoughts that are being pushed at me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you are not allowing them the center stage... Say there is a mind that pressures you towards, I don't know, thoughts of ill will.
[SPEAKER_01]: Somebody knows you.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you were to intentionally now go towards those thoughts, you know exactly what you will think.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're not doing that, so the pressure is there, but there is no specific thoughts of hatred that come from you.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are you left with there and then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, in your state, like, even imagine now, whatever subtle pressure you might be feeling on account of some hindrance, you're not allowing the center stage in regard to that very pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are you left with then, now?
[SPEAKER_01]: The pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course, the pressure is there, but broadly speaking...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, your body... Just basically here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're left with here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not... and that here and now, there, it's not being thought through a taken-up pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's what you're left with by not allowing intentions to take up the pressure.
[SPEAKER_04]: And if you start, like, thinking it as a way to... Yeah, I was gonna say that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, like, sometimes people would then think, aha, so I'll think here and now to not exit the pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, but that's now your pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, although it's the same here and now,
[SPEAKER_01]: You arrived at it completely from the opposite directions.
[SPEAKER_01]: The here-and-now that you often hear about, it's like you focus, you get to it, you get to it, you get to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, no, the here-and-now is what you are left with.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you could see how it was maybe right at some point, to some degree, with somebody.
[SPEAKER_01]: They arrived at it rightly, and then they mystify the here-and-now, and then subsequently, as that has been repeated thousands of times, people forgot the whole context of the actual travel
[SPEAKER_01]: And journey to it, right one.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they just start, no, just here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nibbāna is already here.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just focus on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just stop this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just just just kind of be present and all of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like what I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like you you remain on this sheet of glass because the other one, the other side remains identical, looks identical.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you see no difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is a difference whether you are in left with here and now, through your
[SPEAKER_01]: So, here and now is the result.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not something you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the result of something you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can't just, through a shortcut, just focus on here and now and bypass the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that will be taken up in the same way.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you might... it might be...
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know...
[SPEAKER_03]: Simultaneously, you're asking a question, like, at the right time, and then, to regain perspective.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, you latch on to that, asking a question, and that becomes your method.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your method, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just start doing it blindly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you don't see that it was just a refrain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's inevitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you will be doing it to a degree.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not going to be perfect the first time.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's why the instruction has to remain unobscured and keep pointing you and you keep reminding yourself of where the actual emphasis and the right work is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you start... you ask a question at the right time, you establish the perspective, you don't allow the pressuring, you know, peripheral cloud of thoughts to crystallize through your own ignorant efforts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then,
[SPEAKER_01]: You slip, you get caught in it, but then when you catch yourself that that's what you've been doing, you know, like, okay, but now that needs to be included rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, in regard to that, I don't repeat the same mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or I try to, like, foresee it before it's... before I allow it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you progress.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you catch yourself and then you think, oh, but this is actually not a problem, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the wrong view is the worst possible thing a person can do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, even from the saṃsāra point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, for that sole reason, you won't stay on the right level.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't endure the pressure of somebody in front of your door on the right level, because you would think you don't have to.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, you have somebody pressuring you to open the door.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've been panicking inside, and moving, and getting closer, or going away, or trying to cement the door, or, looking, throw a bomb outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, eventually, you sort of calm down, because you recognize, yeah, it's still, but the point is the door is not open.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why don't I calm down these thoughts while I'm inside?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you calm them down, again, not through denial, not through wishing there's nobody from the door.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just... just let me not have that last say in their crystallization.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just keep my mind free from those images in the center stage, while they're there.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you know they're there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, allow the center stage, you know exactly what's going to come even before it comes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know they're there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know what they are already, even without thinking them explicitly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you realize you do that and then the pressure can't touch you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you can have hundred many people in front of the door or creatures trying to pressure you to open it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only reason you were pressured is when those images were taking the center stage through your own ignorant intention of placing them there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why Arahant's behavior is... there is no measurable, imperceivable difference between private and public.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in private, he's so in public, as in public, he's in private.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no... there's no change there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, just to go back to his example, let's say, eh... there's a question,
[SPEAKER_00]: But it is the case that, in that moment, there is a sense of anxiety.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is a sense of, maybe, like, obligation or, yeah, that I need to ask a question right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: That, yeah, opening the door.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's to act out of that, to ignore that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's a subtle...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, not... yeah, not quite.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of coming to the door handle and...
[SPEAKER_01]: But it wouldn't really be opening the door.
[SPEAKER_01]: Opening the door is when you act, because the pressure... the hindrances are not going to pressure you towards learning more about the dhamma or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your desperate efforts might go in that direction, because you still try to get rid of who's in front of the door.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, fundamentally, opening the door is, you know, when you act towards the pressures.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you really give in.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I said, as long as that's not done, you're still safe.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, yes, of course, once you become confident in that, you could realize, yeah, but I don't even have to think about the door.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't even have to think about who's in front of the door.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only problem is the dumb pressure here and now, through, intentionally, through ignorant intentions, allowing those images associated with it to take the center stage.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, it's kind of... it sounds like it can easily become on that level.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, oh, I asked the question.
[SPEAKER_01]: I acted out of it, didn't I?
[SPEAKER_01]: I made a mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, no, you haven't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're still inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: The door is still closed.
[SPEAKER_01]: You haven't acted out.
[SPEAKER_01]: You haven't acted out of the major doubt and abandoned the training.
[SPEAKER_01]: You haven't acted out on account of the hindrance of sensuality and broke the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: You haven't acted out on account of anger and punched somebody or said something really, like, furious.
[SPEAKER_01]: You haven't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, mentally, I've been getting to the door and wanting to do it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the training.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, and I've been asking these stupid questions this whole time, just really... That's the training.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you get to recognize that as like, okay, now I refine it within the indoor environment.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is still no opening of the door.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not incidental.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind wants to confuse you about what you do inside, so that that makes no difference whether the door is open or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's how it's going to feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is a huge difference whether the door is open or not.
[SPEAKER_04]: I was going to say, like, because it's... acting out doesn't mean doing some action while there is a pressuring state of mind, because you have... you're going to be doing something while there is a pressuring state of mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's whether what you're doing is, like, really rooted in that pressuring state of mind, as in, like, what it wants you to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Opening the door.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even within that, yeah, even within that, in the beginning, it will be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the asking question might be rooted in the pressuring state of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's see.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still not on the level of opening the door for what you're obviously pressured towards.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's going to be rooted, like, you pacing inside of your... of the room, with the door closed, and coming close to the door, and walking away.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all determined by the pressure at the outside of the door.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'll just stop it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that will now be determined by the stuff that's in front of your door.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll just sit still, motionless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is a pressure that I'm under, because somebody's in front of my door trying to make me to open it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever you do will be rooted in it, but it's like, you recognize, okay,
[SPEAKER_01]: By not allowing it to spill out, it's still contained.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the training now, once it's contained.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there is a difference between that, because, as I said, the whole point of Mara making you confused is so you see that there is no... you think there is no difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I'm confused in here, I might be confused...
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter, I might open the door.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still a better type of confusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a better type of pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: You should replace
[SPEAKER_01]: The happiness of household life with the happiness of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_01]: The happiness of outdoor projects with the happiness of indoor peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: You should replace the pain of the outdoor engagements with the pain of indoor pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, eventually, you would abandon that too.
[SPEAKER_04]: And is that also... is there something relevant there as well, about basically, kind of, prioritizing...
[SPEAKER_04]: I suppose, like, doing things in the right order, in terms of, like, prioritizing the things that you are clear about,
[SPEAKER_04]: Rather than trying to, for example, like you were talking about, once you're inside the door, then you can start, like, not allowing the images to crystallize, you know, so that you don't even have to do that part, and then you can be at peace.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, you know, from the point of view of somebody who's, like, still fully, very much pressured, it's like, oh, that sounds very nice.
[SPEAKER_04]: Let me quickly try and do that part, so as to not have to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And actually, that won't work.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, it's... No, and you feel it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the right information remains there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: To be, eventually, to land on the right thing, if you keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, no, definitely, there is... there is a whole sequence to this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you could be trying to not allow the center stage while your door is freaking wide open.
[SPEAKER_01]: And things just coming in and out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Actions, speech, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, yeah, you're just revolving around abstract ideas, even if you had the right instruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, no, the training is, you gotta learn, like, for the door to remain closed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, take on that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's gonna feel pressuring now, because before you used to roam around wherever you wanted.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, yeah, but that's why you were prey to suffering wherever you went.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is it also...
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not just like, well, today the door was closed.
[SPEAKER_03]: This week the door was closed.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like... Yeah, it needs to stay closed.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, and it's not like I do it now and then later.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I'll close it for, you know, five days, open it on the weekends or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, I suppose if somebody is absolutely wild, asutava, unrestrained, it's
[SPEAKER_01]: It could be a way to start, to eventually have your doors closed all the time, but you've got to recognize that there's nowhere near the necessary threshold for any successful practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yes, some people need to work towards the threshold.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's important to qualify this, because if you say, well, yes, start by having a door closed three or four days, they'll think, okay, by doing this absolute sub-par levels, I am also practicing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you're just getting closer to the level where you could start practicing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which, of course, you could argue it's a formal practice, but it's not the dhamma practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like preparatory practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: I've been thinking
[SPEAKER_03]: Kind of, maybe a rough marker, just to kind of, kind of gauge, to gauge where you're at, would be, yeah, what what what you're still opening, actually opening the door to.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like your, like your work, your sort of worst moment, in a sense.
[SPEAKER_03]: What you're still getting at.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's, well, yeah, and then you might say, like, you're not opening the door, but you're still peeking through the curtains.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, oh, hold on, but that means I'm still concerned.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm still pressured by the outside, so I'm still acting towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you might not be peeking through the curtains, but as I said, you still come and you just, just, just think about pressing the handle, even if you know you're not going to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's that refinement of the purification of your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, as I said, if you go in that direction, the distinction that I said between thoughts just popping up on their own in the center stage and thoughts being placed in the center stage through their own ignorant intention, it's the difference between saṃsāra and nibbāna, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing else.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like the root of all the problems.
[SPEAKER_03]: And clarifying that, or clarifying this as well, just like the door, what acts as, what counts as acting out, the door rings on, is done practically.
[SPEAKER_01]: No other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, no other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yes, from the point of view of eventually not being moved by any pressure, when you think back, pacing inside of the room on account of the pressure was acting out.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he wasn't acting out, acting out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you... you press your cigars, you... there's anger knocking at the door, and you don't open it, you care about it, and then you start to... you're just enduring that, and it's still there, and you're still... there's pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I'll just keep knowing that it's at the door, examine it, discern it, and then the thought
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you just acted out there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your discernment is doing something, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's... it is doing something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is doing something, but...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a doing of the discernment of just reinforcing the fact that the door is closed.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... it's the simile of the purifying... purifying of the gold in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, when you're purifying... when you're separating the coarse impurities from the liquid mass,
[SPEAKER_01]: When you put aside the stuff you want to keep, you take lots of impurities with it, just not as coarse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, when you start purifying that, you put further aside stuff you want to keep, it still contains all the impurities.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, technically, you are still acting out, you are still taking on other impurities.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but at the expense of dropping a coarser one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can't be, as I said before, like with a tweezer, picking microscopic impurities in the gold, what is like a lump of excrement floating around.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just... well, that's like... makes absolutely no difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the problem is not like, oh, I acted out, I asked the question and I have to have this...
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is, then, whether you have perspective in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, yeah, but the door is not open.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not ideal, sure, but now I get perspective and I recognize that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's already confidence born from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so I can think about it, even if it's out of pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I'm not going towards the door, and I'm not thinking in terms of opening the door.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, eventually, you realize, but why am I even thinking about it, in that sense?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why am I even allowing center stage for those thoughts to come forward, when I already know the answer?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just a compulsion, a pressure to allow it, to place itself, to crystallize itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I won't do even that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's all, you know, even from the start, you know, when somebody shuts the door by taking on a life of the eight precepts,
[SPEAKER_01]: And they finally shut their door, but then they hold it shut.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every second of their life, they're leaning into the door and squeezing the handle so that it's not opened.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like, yeah, you might start like that, and probably many people would, but then you recognize, hold on, I don't need to hold it, because it can't be opened on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only way for that door to open, it cannot be open accidentally, nor open from the outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only way to open it is me to actively open it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't need to keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just need to not break them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that in itself will cause doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will then blur the line where the door is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if people even allow, people that are still dependent on gripping the door out of fear, and feeling justified in doing so, if you tell them you gotta let go of the door, for them, that's like saying you have to open it and go and dance with what's in front of the door.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, there is no difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why they'll continue clutching at the door, which is the whole essence of silvādhāparamāsa.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't know how to relax.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't know how to endure calmly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, yeah, you don't know, like... You don't know where the... Where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_04]: You don't know where the problem actually comes from.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because what happens if you let go of the door?
[SPEAKER_01]: Your mind gets filled with the doubt, what if that door opens on its own?
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like, that's your practice now.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's your training.
[SPEAKER_01]: Developing your mind, yourself, in regard to the mind of doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why Sīlavāt-paramāsā and the doubt go hand in hand.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by then accepting that the training is on the level of doubt, developing your mind in regard to doubt, not acting out of it, enduring it on the right level, not allowing intentional thoughts to crystallize, they're rooted in it, all of that,
[SPEAKER_01]: See, in order to accept that, you need to abandon your previous notions of the training being holding the door as tightly as possible and doing magical visualizations that will magically, somehow, miraculously remove the pressure from the front of my door one day.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just won't be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, oh, yeah, those people don't do the right practice because they refuse to give up the wrong practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I mean, in a way, the door is not open, but another way, you're not... Yeah, you're not really developing anything inside, because you're still very much concerned with the outside.
[SPEAKER_04]: As in, like, the thing is, if you were to stop holding it, the problem is, you'd just be opening it.
[SPEAKER_04]: You don't see any... Yeah, you would be opening it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not holding the door means opening it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's a lot of pressure, you don't open it, and then you don't even want to look, you don't even know about what's outside there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you just...
[SPEAKER_01]: Wish for it to go away, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just shut down.
[SPEAKER_02]: Try to shut everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or just get into meditation techniques.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, just to ignore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you still don't want to train?
[SPEAKER_01]: You still don't want to train in regard to the existing pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You still want it to simply go away, not be there.
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, if you're sitting in your room and you have this, whatever, pressuring thought, now it's like, okay, let me just go for a walk to calm down or something.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that's acting out of pressure.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, you can go for a walk.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you can... Well, it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could say it is acting out of pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, not to the extent of opening the door.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: By allowing that, by recognizing that, you are kind of at the same time seeing the difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But by just doubling down now and saying, oh, that's pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no, no, no, to everything automatically.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wishing that self-cancellation on the inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, then, see, I can either cancel the problem outside of the door or wish for it or cancel me inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, that's the presumed kind of pathway of resolution, which is sensuality and self-mortification in its principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's like, yeah, there is pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm going for a walk or I'm doing this or that, but I know for sure, I recognize it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no confusion in regard to what extent that goes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yes, ideally, I don't want to be moved even to that extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in order to arrive there, I first have to get used to this extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, go for walk every day, if it maintains you not opening the door, if it allows you to stay with the pressure, if it enables you to not allow, through the ignorant intention, crystallization of the images concerned with the outside, with sensuality, with your will, with acting out on that level.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, yeah, I'll go for a walk and perspective remains.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eventually, as I said, when you get used to that,
[SPEAKER_01]: Going for a walk will become too coarse.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't even have to do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Also, maybe like, whatever you do inside is like highlighting the actual door that you're not opening.
[SPEAKER_02]: That practice, you know, that the practice that is important, the core practice of not opening the door.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever you do inside highlights that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm going to do something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, let me just highlight the thing that I shouldn't be doing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: As long as it's not that, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's what determines whatever else you can do.
[SPEAKER_04]: As long as it's not that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's going to be, as I said before, it's going to be... sometimes it will be more obvious, sometimes less.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's the training.
[SPEAKER_01]: And also the point is then to... which obviously, as I said, with the right instruction, hopefully you won't fall into a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: of then thinking, okay, going for a walk is the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: By magically going for a walk, pressure will resolve itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, no, this is something you do on account of being pressured by not acting out to the full extent, but not being able to remain unmoved either.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you still know where the practice is, where the training is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just, as I said, when purifying the gold, you have to, for a while, put aside gold with the other impurities and can't possibly be concerned with everything all at once, because that will make you lose sight of the obvious impurities that you should have... could have easily abandoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's... that's exactly the pathway people would take.
[SPEAKER_01]: Aha!
[SPEAKER_01]: Close the door.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pressure builds up.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to ask questions.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's routine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pressure should do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then end up becoming no.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I didn't even... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just just absolute denial.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, people would arrive, it's like, oh, well, no to everything, makes no difference what I do.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would be the next jump into conclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you've been saying no, trying to deny stuff on account of the pressure, that then led you to a view that it doesn't matter what you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all the same anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, but that's not quite true, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if we take it for the sake of an argument to be true, what you do then?
[SPEAKER_01]: If it doesn't matter what you do, why is then your next course of action going to open the door?
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter what you do, so why don't you just keep it closed?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it doesn't matter what I do, thus I'll go back outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's usually what it leads to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Self-mortification.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has to just revert you back all the way where you started.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you shunned.
[SPEAKER_01]: The bait that you tried to avoid and not learn about or feel pressured about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ran on top of a mountain like a deer herd did.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stubbed out and then just went back straight, not knowing the difference between what's the bait, what the threshold is, and where the door handle is.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you could dive into... it's not really sensory.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like a sense of deprivation, I guess.
[SPEAKER_03]: But... or like take on austerities which are particularly... which are unnecessary for that... for what you're actually able to withstand.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then... but you're... but you are holding them.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, do you learn within that container?
[SPEAKER_03]: You're holding what?
[SPEAKER_03]: Like...
[SPEAKER_03]: The austerities?
[SPEAKER_03]: Technically.
[SPEAKER_03]: The deprivations?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, technically.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you wouldn't learn anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're looking completely in a wrong place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even, as I said, you're emulating the right thing, seemingly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Internally, it's done for completely different reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, and yeah, that's...
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a good point.
[SPEAKER_01]: The difference between sense restraint...
[SPEAKER_01]: Sense restraint is not deprivation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sense restraint is saying no to the right things, to the extent that the pressure arises, and then train in regard to the pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't shy away from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't try to deny it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Deprivation, it's a view of if I say no to things, pressure won't touch me.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I just blindly increase things I deny, I will be free from the mental pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's as ignoble as engaging with sensuality, as they would say.
[SPEAKER_04]: If I'm still touched by pressure, it just means I must increase the weight another notch.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I double down.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not just saying no to more things.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's what's missing.
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I've always been curious about this step from virtue and sensitivity.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, it's kind of... it's often just said, like, virtue and sensitivity.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, they're kind of simultaneous, or like...
[SPEAKER_03]: But, no, no, it's... yeah, it's quite clear, I think, that virtue
[SPEAKER_03]: There's a reason why it's mentioned first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, sense restraint involves intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the sense restraint in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not on the level of just saying no.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like the monk doesn't look at the sight that's provocative of lust then and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means it can be a different thing at different times.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes the same thing might not be provoking lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: That might not be the intention why you're looking at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, but if you just adopt the view that, you know, the thing is judged by its content, that's why I must say no to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, some things are obvious, always unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's kind of what virtue addresses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things you don't do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the training in sense restraint is a lot more nuanced than just say no to anything you want to see.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, no, it's why I want to see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why the eyes go this way?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why does the ear wander?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then it's like, oh, now, yeah, I know that it's rooted in sensuality, in pleasure or distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: I say no to
[SPEAKER_01]: But it can be the same thing that then it's not rooted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you don't say no to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, but it's still good to say no to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Saying no to it when you shouldn't obscures the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Removes the basis for training there and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why are you doing it then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you doing it to train the mind or are you doing it to fulfill some projected ideal of austerity and purity?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's obviously very ignorant.
[SPEAKER_01]: The difference between thoughts taking the center stage on their own, which is basically not the center stage,
[SPEAKER_01]: And thoughts taking the center stage through your own allowance is the difference in your intention, nothing else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you have intention to not allow them to crystallize, or do you have intention that allows them to crystallize?
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you know, if you're not... if you're not being training in regard to coarser forms of your own intention, this discerning them, seeing them, be pressured by them, endure them, not acting out of them, it's like you're not gonna see this.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll make no difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will sound like be here now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just focus on the present moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not going to see the whole trajectory of the travel in between, or around.